<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of their Majesties Wisdom in the nomination of some reverend persons to the vacant arch-bishopricks and bishopricks occasioned by the scandalous reflections of unreasonable men / by a minister of London.</title>
            <author>Minister of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11061677</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11061677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1433:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of their Majesties Wisdom in the nomination of some reverend persons to the vacant arch-bishopricks and bishopricks occasioned by the scandalous reflections of unreasonable men / by a minister of London.</title>
                  <author>Minister of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Patronage, Ecclesiastical.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:46190:1"/>
            <q>
               <p>I Have been, according to my Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, not a negligent Obſerver of the Genius and Humour of the ſeveral Sects and Profeſſions in Religion; and upon the whole matter, I do in my Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi rend="blackletterType">Church of England,</hi> to be the beſt conſtituted Church this day in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World; and that as to the main, the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of it, are excellently framed to make men ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religious, ſecuring men on the one hand from the wild Freaks of Enthuſiaſm, and on the other hand from the groſs Follies of Superſtition.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Tillotſon <hi>in a Sermon before King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the Second.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46190:1"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THEIR MAJESTIES Wiſdom, In the late NOMINATION of ſome <hi rend="blackletterType">Reverend Perſons</hi> To the Vacant Arch-Biſhopricks AND BISHOPRICKS: Occaſioned by the Scandalous Reflections OF UNREASONABLE MEN.</p>
            <p>By a Miniſter of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46190:2"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are three ſorts of Perſons whoſe Spirits I know ſo well, that I am very well ſatisfied before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, I ſhall not want their unſeemly as well as unkind Reflections, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things ſaid in theſe few ſheets.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the man ſo reſolute for the late King <hi>James,</hi> that he cares not if the whole Kingdom, was nothing but a Common Slaughter-houſe, and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb facs="tcp:46190:3"/>
thereof, were involved in an utter ruine, together with our Religion, and Liberties, provided King <hi>James</hi> was at the Helm again.</p>
            <p>The other is the very High flown <hi>Church-man,</hi> who rather than part with ſomething, that is but like the pairings of his Nails, will venture the whole Conſtitution of the Church.</p>
            <p>The laſt is the <hi>looſe Whigg,</hi> who notwithſtanding all his former Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſatisfaction if he might enjoy the Liberty of his Conſcience without moleſtation, yet ſtill is very uneaſie, as if nothing would content him but the Power of a Committee-man or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrator, and is daily extolling the Juſtice of the late Civil War, and where he dares, juſtifying the Murder
<pb facs="tcp:46190:3"/>
of that Incomparable Prince, King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>Now Reader, to be plain with thee, as I expect bad words from theſe perſons, ſo I will promiſe thee to be Eaſie under them; becauſe I think it much more for a mans Credit, to be ſpoke Ill, than Well of, by men of ſuch Kidneys; for ſuch ſpirited men have been the Bane of all ſorts of Society, Religious, as well, as Civil, in moſt Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>And therefore if thou findeſt any thing that cuts with too keen an Edge, and looks too ſharp, in the following Treatiſe, I muſt begg thee, to believe it is intended only againſt ſuch Bigots as theſe, and not againſt any good man whatever. For I am not afraid to tell the World, that wherever I meet
<pb facs="tcp:46190:4"/>
with a good and modeſt man, let him be of any Opinion, or Perſwaſion, never ſo different from my own, yet I love him as a Friend, and according to my power will treat him as a Brother. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46190:4"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THEIR Majeſties Wiſdom In the NOMINATION of ſome BISHOPS TO THE Vacant Sees.</head>
            <p>THere is nothing in all the Ages of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, hath done more Miſchief to the Church of God than violent Prejudices and Paſſionate Reſolutions to adhere to thoſe Prejudices, tho' never ſo haſtily and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly taken up either againſt Things or Perſons; for through the influence of theſe, Men have been deaf to all Argument and Reaſon, to all wiſe and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46190:5"/>
cool Thoughts and Diſcourſes, and you can as well almoſt remove a Mountain, as ſtir theſe Men from their fixed and determined Opinions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions ſo haſtily taken up.</p>
            <p>It is no doubt, but this is the main Reaſon, of ſo many Mens (otherwiſe Men of Conſideration in the World, both for Learning and other Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities) ſtanding out and declaring againſt the late Revolution, and whiſpering, nay, the more is the pity, publickly abuſing the Government, as it is in the Hands of their preſent Majeſties, (whom God grant long to live, and to ſucceed in all their Juſt and Pious Undertakings,) and impeaching all thoſe Conſcientious Perſons, that having taken the eaſie Oaths impoſed by Authority upon them, as Men that have forſaken the Principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and turned their backs upon their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Obligations to the late King <hi>James:</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, in gratification of theſe Principles of Prejudice, are now full of nothing but Rage and Fury, which they vent by all manner of unſeemly Words and Speeches upon their Majeſties late Nomination of thoſe worthy Men to fill up the Sees of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks, vacant by their Predeceſſors denying to take the Oaths enjoyned them by the Supreme Power of the Kingdom. Alas! you cannot come into the Company of ſome ſort of Men, but your Ears are filled and dinned with nothing but <hi>the Church! the Church!</hi> Oh the <hi>Church</hi> is utterly deſtroyed, put into the hands of falſe Loons, who will betray her Rites, break down her Fences, ſet up Presbytery, or elſe countenance Anarchy and Confuſion, and give up the Order of Biſhops, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46190:5"/>
with the grave and ſolemn, and therefore neceſſary way of publick Worſhipping of God by a ſtated Liturgy: and that is not all, but they muſt be cryed down too, as Men of no Honour nor Conſcience, in taking the Places of Men ſo good and deſerving. And what particular brands of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy and Reproach are fixed upon the Reverend, Learned and Pious Dean of <hi>St. Pauls,</hi> whom their Majeſties have Nominated to the See of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> things, which as he is altogether unworthy of, ſo thanks be to God, he is a Man of that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Courage, and of that great Prudence, that he knows how to do his Duty to God, and to their Majeſties Perſons and Government, without being ruffled or diſcompoſed by ſuch unmannerly and baſe Reflections, which have no Original, but from the corrupt and diſingenuous, malicious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful minds of thoſe who have been all along Enemies to him, becauſe he hath been a ſteady Friend to Truth and Chriſtian Moderation, and hath lived bewailing, but no wayes countenancing or encouraging thoſe Paſſions of all Sides and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which have been the Bane of Religion it ſelf, as well as of the Safety and Honour of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore becauſe the Clamour is ſo great, and runs ſo high, and the effects of it may be of ſo very deſtructive Conſequence to their Majeſties Government, both in Church and State, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to do Right to thoſe Reverend Perſons, who have ſo greatly Merited by their learned Pens and Pious Lives, as well as to their Majeſties Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at this time, in pitching upon Men to ſucceed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46190:6"/>
thoſe who have voluntarily quitted their Stations in the Church, and I do not doubt but to make it plain, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſo far from being in danger of ruine by theſe worthy Men, that ſhe will gather ſtrength more and more, and look with a more acceptable Countenance amongſt the general part of the Nation; yea, even Diſſenters themſelves, who are but tolerably wiſe and thoughtfull.</p>
            <p>It is very well known to thoſe, who have been impartial Readers of the Hiſtory of the Church, ſince the Reformation, by what means ſhe hath loſt ground, and upon what ſcore the Non-conformiſts grew up in Intereſt againſt her. To paſs by the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, becauſe it was a Reign of great Factions amongſt Men of different Intereſts, and who too many of them rather ſought to ſerve themſelves of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, than to ſerve the Reformation it ſelf, we will begin with Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s coming to the Crown, who though ſhe was certainly always a Proteſtant, after ſhe came to ſome Years of diſcerning in her Inclination, yet was forced to comply when Popery was upermoſt, ſo as to keep her ſelf out of danger: For without doubt, had ſhe profeſſed her ſelf an open Enemy to Popery, and uſed any other Publick Devotions than what were then in faſhion, and eſtabliſhed by Law, ſhe had fallen a Sacrifice to the Biggottry of her Siſter, and to <hi>Gardiner</hi>'s Rage and Revenge; but however when ſhe came to the Crown her ſelf, ſhe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after a very little Temporizing, which we ought to believe Neceſſity of State was the only Reaſon of, ſhe fell to reforming the Church, and it may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46190:6"/>
advanced a Number of as good Men to the Vacant Biſhopricks, both for Learning and Piety, as any of her four Succeſſors have done ſince. And here was the firſt falſe ſtep by which the Church hath rather loſt than got ground ever ſince; for though ſhe preferred Men of ſo great Worth, Men of ſuch ſignal Holineſs, and who upon the account of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Baniſhment or other Sufferings in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s dayes were very acceptabe to all the Men of the Kingdom, who were then Proteſtants, and who by vertue of their exemplary Converſations, were very well fitted to ſtop the Mouths of gain ſayers, and by degrees to win over the Papiſts, eſpecially thoſe who were only ſo by the ſtrength of their Education; yet at the ſame time ſhe would not ſuffer theſe Men, though of her own raiſing, to influence her into any little Alterations or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which might at that time have ſettled the Church upon a larger bottom, and prevented that after Schiſm which was made by ſome Men, who by their Travels in <hi>Germany</hi> and another place had ſucked in ſome very narrow ſtingy Principles, which by a little Condeſcention they certainly had been ſhamed out of, or elſe put out of Capacity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding the common People, as they afterwards did, to the great detriment of the Church. She had been brought up in the pompous, gawdy way of Popiſh Worſhip, and therefore notwithſtanding all the modeſt Applications of her Pious Biſhops, who valued ſubſtantial Religion above all other things, ſhe continued her Zeal for Ceremonies, and ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and maintained them all her Reign; which thô ſhe might lawfully do, and there was no moral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46190:7"/>
Evil in them, as hath been ſufficiently made out by many learned Pens ever ſince; yet ſome wiſe Men think, that an Abatement of one or two Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and changeing four or five Phraſes in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book,</hi> would have enlarged the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Pale, and prevented all the Puritans deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her; for to give thoſe early Malecontents their juſt due, and I am not afraid to ſpeak it, they never got into the good Opinion and Affection of the People by any ſtrength of Argument, by any real and ſolid Proofs of Scripture, but by popular Harangues, and odious Names fixt upon the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and the Common-Prayer-Book, and they wrought more upon the unthinking and yet zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly-inclin'd Vulgar, by calling a thing a Rag of <hi>Rome,</hi> a Mark of the Beaſt, and an Antichriſtian Uſage, than ever they did by rational and well-weighed Exceptions to any thing enjoyned by the Laws of the Land; all which Occaſions of Miſchief had been prevented, as very wiſe Men think, if the Biſhops at that time could have had their Will of the Queen, and got her to Condeſcend to thoſe Abatements in which they thought the Church ſo little concerned as to her Being or Well-being, that they did believe they could thereby ſtifle the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and have left them to be the Heads of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Party, which would quickly have dwindled into nothing. But however, Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> kept to her Point reſolvedly, and by her pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and unwavering Government kept the Party down for forty four Years together; upon whoſe Death, and King <hi>James</hi> the firſt's juſt Acceſſion to the Crown, the Party hoping ſome advantage from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46190:7"/>
his Education under <hi>Buchanan,</hi> a Friend of theirs, Petitioned for Relief, and he to ſettle the Minds of his Subjects commands a Conference at <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Court,</hi> where certainly had there not been too ſtiff an adherence to ſome few things, which might without danger have been altered, had not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops then, (though very good Men, yet not able to foreſee the effects of theſe Mens Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, upon the Common People in future times, and truſting to the Zeal of the then King to ſtand by and aſſiſt them,) I ſay, had not the Biſhops then had ſuch an Aſcendant throughout the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference over the King, which he was well pleaſed withall, having by the contrary Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> been ſo roughly handled all his time; I ſay, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that Conference had terminated in a great advantage to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan Party was not ſo numerous, nor conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrong, as afterwards; nor yet their Diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſo great as they have been ſince, a very little and eaſie Condeſcention had ſpoiled the Market of the Deſigning men, both Gentry and Miniſters too, and we had not heard of, nor felt thoſe Miſeries in the Nation, that God knows both our Anceſtors and we have done ever ſince: And ſo this Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity was loſt, and the Party grew ſtronger and ſtronger all King <hi>James</hi> his time, and talked as loud as they durſt againſt Will-worſhip and beggerly Elements, as they were pleaſed to call our Prayers and Ceremonies, by which they continued to cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate abundance of eaſie People, and to inſinuate a Belief into them that they only Worſhipped God and Adminiſtred Ordinances according to the Pattern
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46190:8"/>
in the Mount, as they Phraſed it; and that which gave them a great advantage over and above their Pretences to a more Pure way of Worſhip, was the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Match, and upon the Failure of that the <hi>French</hi> Marriage: for then they eaſily made the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous World believe that nothing but Popery was at the door, and that it was impoſſible, when a Papiſt lay in a King's Boſom, but that he muſt be influenced by her Charms to Favour her Religion as well as to Love her Perſon: and the truth of it is, this was too great an advantage to be put into a reſtleſs and deſigning Party's Hand, and they made uſe of it accordingly; for by this means they got a great Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in moſt of the Counties and Corporations of <hi>England,</hi> whereby were returned a major part of Men affected to them to the Houſe of Commons, and what the Effects of their Counſels were, and what Spirits they ſhewed, I had rather any one ſhou'd tell than my ſelf; for though I do believe many of them meant very well, yet by the ſequel we find others made a noiſe in the Houſe, and found fault, on purpoſe to be bought off by the Court, and put into Poſts of Honour and Profit together, and then we find how quickly their Opinion of State Affairs altered; for that which was before the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Grievance, was now neceſſary for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government. Now at the ſame time, while the Puritans thus enlarged their Intereſt throughout the Kingdom, the Biſhops on the other ſide carryed things with a very high Hand, having the Countenance of King and Laws, and uſed ſome Men very roughly, yea and thoſe many of them too who were the Peoples Darlings, and made
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46190:8"/>
the greater Darlings too by reaſon of their harſh uſage of them; ſo that there was nothing in the Nation but endeavours by Fines and Puniſhments, Corporal as well as Pecuniary, to ſuppreſs the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on the one ſide, and Cabals and Clubs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Nobility, Gentry, and diſcontented Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, to pluck the Plumes of the Hierarchy, and to weaken the Biſhops Power, together with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies, as they thought them, of their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts on the other ſide: And the truth of it is, the Book of Sports, together with ſome other, I fancy (though I am tender of judging) unneceſſary Innovations, which Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> (thô otherwayes a very good Man) countenanced, and the Zeal for which he rewarded with the beſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments of the Nation, theſe gave a very great Advantage to the Puritan-Party to get into the Hearts and Affections of many well and religiouſly inclined People throughout the Nation; and to give them their due, they were not wanting to make uſe of it accordingly; and therefore when King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, through his preſſing Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties called a Parliament, the People being allarm'd at the new Supra-conformity, all thoſe things brought into the Church, which they were made to believe were introductions to Popery, nay, Popery it ſelf, they generally pitched upon ſuch Men to repreſent them as would look into theſe things, and provide ſuch remedies for them as were thought at that time neceſſary; which Parliament at its firſt ſitting down, certainly had abundance of great Patriots of their Countrey, paſſionate Lovers of their King, and true Admirers of the Church in its eſſential
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46190:9"/>
Conſtitution, ſuch as my Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> &amp;c. and deſigned none of thoſe things which afterwards through the craft and ſubtilty of too many of their Fellow-Members were brought to paſs.</p>
            <p>And here now another Opportunity was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church-mens hands to ſave the Church, and to have prevented that Bloody War, the miſerable Effects of which we feel to this very day; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had there been any good Temper, and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Commands of a true Chriſtian Spirit, at this time our breaches had been healed, and our Church had been like a compacted City, at Unity with it ſelf, and all thoſe Notorious Schiſms and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, together with all thoſe filthy Opinions and Doctrines of Devils, which like a violent Innun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation broke in upon the Church, had certainly been prevented: But alas, we then did not, or would not know the things that belonged to our Peace. And here I muſt change the Tables, and charge another ſort of Men with one of the greateſt Miſtakes, if not one of the greateſt Crimes imaginable, and plainly ſhow that when Men, tho' pretending the greateſt Conſcience, fancy themſelves furniſhed with power to back them, even they are as ready to ſacrifice the publick good and Peace of Church and State to their own private Paſſions, to their own Luſt and Revenge, as thoſe they formerly complained of as their greateſt Oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>For we find that when Archbiſhop <hi>Williams,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Morton</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> and other very learned, pious and moderate Divines, were appointed to meet at <hi>Jeruſalem-Chamber</hi> in the Deans Houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> Dr. <hi>Seaman,</hi> and others
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46190:9"/>
who pretended diſſatisfaction at ſome parts of the Churches Conſtitution, thoſe Biſhops and learned Men, made ſuch Offers, drew up ſuch Terms of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, and made ſuch Condeſcentions, that all wiſe Men expected nothing but an happy Union. There was nothing that I can meet withall, that the other Party objected againſt, and made matter of ſcruple or uneaſineſs to the Party called <hi>Puritans,</hi> but they were ready to part withall, tho' they had before defended them ſo well; Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, as any one knows that hath read his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the three innocent Ceremonies; for by the by, you muſt know, that Party was not run ſo far as now, as to write Books againſt Dioceſan Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy and ſtated Liturgies. Now if any Man ask me where things ſtuck at this ſeeming happy jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and what hindered ſuch a bleſſed Accord, as without all doubt would have made the Kingdom inſtead of a Field of Blood, a Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God? Why truly I muſt deal plainly, for I put out theſe Papers with a reſolution to ſpare nor flatter any Party of Men, the Fault now lay at the <hi>Puritans</hi> door, and they who had Complained of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity and Perſecution, and called the Biſhops, both in their Pulpits and private Converſation, by worſe Names, all things truly conſidered, than they did deſerve, only for exacting Conformity to the Laws of the Church, and which they had ſubſcribed with their own Hands to obſerve; why now when they ſaw their Party uppermoſt, and too great a Number, God knows, of the Houſe of Commons to ſide with them, they left theſe great and good Men in the lurch, turned their backs upon their Perſons as well
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46190:10"/>
as upon all thoſe moderate and healing Propoſals they had made; and when Sir <hi>Arthur Hazzlerigg</hi> had the Confidence as well as the diſhoneſty to bring in a Bill for taking away Deans and Chapters Lands, that is, in plain Engliſh, robbing them of what they had as good a riht to legally, as he had to his Eſtate; they, I mean Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> and the reſt, thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo ſecure of the Power of the Nation, that nothing would ſerve their turn but Root and Branch, (a ſpirit too much amongſt their Succeſſors in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples at this very day) and both Epiſcopacy and Liturgy, all muſt be ſacrificed and given up to the Deſigns and Pretences of a prevailing Party, who, God knows, thereby involved three Kingdoms in Blood and Ruine, and have thereby entailed a ſpirit of Antipathy amongſt Neighbouring Families in all parts of the Nation ever ſince: for had this hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Meeting at <hi>Jeruſalem-Chamber</hi> obtained its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired effect, which I am ſure, if I know any thing in Hiſtory, the Conformable Clergy were very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to promote, the War, the diſmal War had been prevented, and all the wofull Effects of it too: For the deſigning Lords and Gentlemen, who had a mind to engroſs the Power and Riches of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into their Hands, to rule both King and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, could never have raiſed Men to have fought their Battels, if they had not wheedled and ſeduced the more eaſie, Gentlemen and the Common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by Pretences that the Cauſe of God and Jeſus Chriſt lay at ſtake, and that if they did not come in to help the Lord againſt the Mighty, Popiſh Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny would over-run them in a Moment, and the pure Ordinances of Chriſt would be mixt and blend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46190:10"/>
with humane Inventions and ſuperſtitious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
            <p>And thus we loſt, through the Pride and Folly of ſome Men, (I ſcarce ever think of it without hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and trouble of mind) one of the beſt Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities that was ever put into Mens hands, to have ſet things right in the Church, and to have united almoſt all the Kingdom in one way of Worſhip, which would have been ſuch a Bleſſing, as is beyond my poor Rhetorick to expreſs.</p>
            <p>And what followed after, let thoſe who have a mind to be informed, read the Hiſtory of the Civil Wars, for I take no pleaſure to write it; only thus much I will ſay, that it ended in the Murder of one of the beſt Princes that ever ſat upon a Throne: A Prince whom nothing but black Malice and deviliſh Revenge dare venture to blot and defame, and whoſe bright and excellent Virtues do ſo upbraid his Murderers, and thoſe who are ſo ready to abet them, that by Lyes and Forgeries they are always endeavouring to leſſen, or elſe flatly to deny them: A Prince, whoſe Name and Memory ought to be, as no doubt it will, precious to all impartial and unprejudiced Men who have any ſenſe of Truth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Religion.</p>
            <p>And this I ſpeak, the rather becauſe I find abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of New Royaliſts, who would make the World believe they are the only Friends to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> (or as they Phraſe it, to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government) and yet at the ſame time heap all the Calumnies and Reproaches upon their glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Grandfather they can, and applaud and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that villanous High Court of Juſtice which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46190:11"/>
brought him to ſuch an untimely end; and at this time ſome of them have reprinted, to give an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Teſtimony to his Royal Grand children of their Dutifulneſs and Loyalty, that falſe and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Anſwer of <hi>Milton</hi> to his Unparallel'd Book, with a vile inſinuation as if it was not his own: But theſe Men, notwithſtanding all their Pretences of Loyalty, muſt give me leave to tell them, there is a Snake in the Graſs, and that we know them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than to believe they purpoſe any Duty to their preſent Majeſties, than as it ſerves their turns, and helps forward thoſe Deſigns which a Man of half an Eye may ſee into, eſpecially if he hath but read over the Hiſtory of the late War.</p>
            <p>Well, things being at this paſs in the Nation, for want of an early accommodation, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſat down in Forty, all things running into no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but diſorder and confuſion, all ſorts of Parties ſtriving to get uppermoſt; the Nation wearied with their various Changes, and hankering after their old Conſtitution of Church and State, by the help of a great General, invited their Natural Prince, after twelve Years Baniſhment, home again; and having been toſſed and tumbled up and down by croſs Winds, longed for a Calm, which they found could not be obtained, but by a return to their Duties to their lawfull Sovereign, and building upon their old Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. And now every Mans Heart was eaſie, unleſs it were ſome particular deep-dyed Criminals, whom the Juſtice of the Nation, for its own Honour ſake muſt needs overtake; I ſay, every Mans Heart almoſt was eaſie, and the two great differing Parties of the Kingdom ſeem to be inclinable to a Conjunction of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46190:11"/>
Intereſt, and nothing was talked of but a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, founded in ſuch Abatements as would bring in all the wiſe and ſober Men of the Kingdom into one way of Worſhip and Communion; and in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this a Commiſſion was iſſued out, and ſome of both Parties met, and many Debates they had, but alas, after all, the old ſpirit, which hath defeated the beſt and moſt profitable Deſigns in the World, I mean the ſpirit of Revenge and Retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſprung up with all fierceneſs and cruelty, and the Sufferers were not mortified enough to forgive thole who had been the occaſion of their Miſeries, and therefore inſtead of bringing them into the ſame Body with themſelves, and thereby ſtrengthning the Intereſt of the Church, they made harder Terms of Communion than there were before the War, and impoſed a New Declaration to be ſubſcribed and read afterwards in publick Churches, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pride of ſome nor the Tenderneſs of others would or could ſubmit to.</p>
            <p>And here again we loſt as fair an Oppertunity of Union as could be deſired, and what have been the effects of it, there is no Man that converſes with Books or himſelf, muſt or can be ignorant of; there were ſome hundreds of Men that afterwards became the Heads of diſcontented Parties, and thoſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for Wealth and Numbers, who would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have ſtaid in the Church upon ſome very few Abatements, and have ſerved God and the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Souls of the People very faithfully, but are now ſo imbittered, that it is not an eaſie thing to bring them back, and to reconcile them to any Terms of Union whatſoever. Good God! that a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46190:12"/>
Nation ſhould be ſo blinded, as thus at all times to conſult their own Paſſions againſt the common good of Chriſtianity, as well as the Safety and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the beſt Conſtituted Church in the World. What hand the Papiſts had in keeping up theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and what advantage they have made of them ever ſince, is apparent to any Man of but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mean Obſervation of things. We were by this means within a very little of utter ruine, both of our Church and State, and the late King <hi>James</hi> to carry on his Deſigns againſt the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſweetned theſe ſort of Men, took them into his Boſom, and gave them ſuch verbal Aſſurances of a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> for Liberty of Conſcience, that (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they talk againſt him now) they then ſlaviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lay at his Feet with fulſome Addreſſes of Thanks, and with Promiſes of Lifes and Fortunes to ſtand by him, by whoſe help and aſſiſtance, had not our preſent Gracious and Noble King ſtept in to our reſcue, the Church of <hi>England</hi> had certainly been born down by thoſe two Parties of Papiſts and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and ſacrificed to the rage and cruel reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them both; though by the way, I am ſure it is no part of the goodneſs, or that ſingular Piety (they pretend to) of too many of our Diſſenters, (for all were not guilty) to run ſo violently, and againſt all reaſon and common experience, into ſuch an Intereſt as was never true to any Promiſes or Oaths that croſſed and thwarted their own Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſecular Deſigns.</p>
            <p>Well, the then Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> coming over as a Sovereign Prince, to vindicate the Hereditary Rights of his Noble Lady, as well as his own, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46190:12"/>
and the States of the Realm Recognizing and Declaring him and his Princeſs King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> which by the way I verily believe, was the only way, (things being in ſuch a Poſture as they were) to ſettle the Nation, notwithſtanding all the talk of a Regency, or any other Expedient. Pray now upon this great Change of Affairs, was there no ſteps made by both Parties to an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation? ſurely now, if ever Mens Eyes might be opened, in order to ſee the Cauſe of their former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and to provide Remedies againſt them for the future; yea, to give a great many good Men their due, and in particular our excellent King and Queen, they with abundance of other Men ſhewed their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to bring the Nation to a due Temper; a thing we all know our Reverend Biſhops in the day of their Afflictions and Fears promiſed; and in order to this, a Commiſſion was iſſued out by the King, in which were named a great many extraordinary Perſons both for Religion and Learning, and who (for the greateſt part of them, as I am well aſſured) had with great Harmony and Agreement prepared things for the Convocation, which the wiſe and well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed part of the Nation did not doubt would have had a very good effect, to bring in many of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; and I am very well ſatisfyed great Numbers of the Laity too into our Communion, and by that means would have weakened the hands of Diviſion, and much laid that ſcurvy Spirit which hath been ſo miſchievous to ſo many of the Churches of Chriſt ever ſince the Apoſtles dayes.</p>
            <p>What was done upon this, I will rather with grief of mind paſs over in ſilence, than bring freſh upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46190:13"/>
the Stage, becauſe it will tend to nothing but exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſeeing all theſe Opportunities have been ſo loſt, which I have named, truly I know no way to keep the Church in a ſtate of Life, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve her from the rough and barbarous hands of her reſolved and ſtubborn Enemies, than to put ſuch Men into Places of Truſt and Command, of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power, whoſe Religion as well as Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whoſe Chriſtian Spirits as well as great Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings may endear the Church to the People, and make them ſee that a Man may be a true and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet be a Pious and a good Man; a thing which the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, too many of them, God knows, (the more is their ignorance or their impudence) have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſwade the People againſt, as if no Man could be a Child of God, and in a State of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that thinks honourably of a Biſhop, or ſerves God (as he ought to do, if he would ſerve him wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) by well digeſted Forms of Prayer. And were ſuch Pious and Holy Men in moſt of the Places of the Church, of low as well as high degree, I am very certain that Separation would loſe ground every day, and our Poſterity would not be leavened with ſuch ſowr and narrow Principles, as we have cauſe to fear they will be, if Fanaticiſm does not loſe its reputation more than it hath done a few Years laſt paſt. And to this end I dare ſay it is, that our excellent King and Queen have Choſen and Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated ſuch Perſons to the ſeveral Vacant Sees. I am no Flatterer, but ſpeak what I know from Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Acquaintance, that they are Men of Prudence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46190:13"/>
and Learning, of Integrity and Honour, who high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly value, and alſo live up to that which we call de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly, Subſtantial Religion, and yet at the ſame time know how to defend, and encourage the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Obſervation of the legal and eſtabliſhed Rites of the Church, and who by Vertue of theſe good Qualities will, and cannot but promote the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Church, both by being Examples of, and alſo by zealous recommending Holy Living to all under their Charge and Care.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding all the Clamours againſt the preſent Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all thoſe falſe as well as vile Reproaches they have attempted to faſten upon him, which can proceed from no other than a Diabolical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I do not doubt but he will prove one of the greateſt Bleſſings to the Church this Age hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; for it is ſuch a Temper as he hath always manifeſted throughout his whole Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation that muſt heal our Breaches, and reſtore us Paths to dwell quietly and ſafely in; and they who accuſe him for not being a true Church-man, I muſt tell them, have framed falſe Notions and Idea's of the Church, and have made it a little Fold, fit to hold none but a Company of hot-headed and violent ſpirited Men: A Notion, which at this time of the day ought to be laid aſide, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing of which the Church <hi>England</hi> will be but a ſmall Party of Men, and loſe every day her Strength and her Reputation, and at laſt will be devoured by thoſe greedy Cormorants that long for her Lands and Poſſeſſions again; and thoſe Men that have the Confidence as well as Silly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46190:14"/>
to call no Men true Church men but ſuch as are ſtretched out to juſt ſuch a length, muſt excuſe me if I tell them, that under pretence of Friendſhip and Love to her, they ſmite her through the fifth Rib, and throw out of her Communion the beſt and moſt pious Members ſhe can and ought to glory in.</p>
            <p>I know I ſhall anger abundance of Men, by theſe juſt, though too ſhort Characters I have given of theſe Worthy and Reverend Perſons; and ſome may think that it looks like a deſign, to leſſen the deſerved value of thoſe, who have forſaken their Biſhopricks, becauſe they could not take the Oaths; but I muſt begg their Pardon, I am, I thank God for it, a Perſon of more Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Juſtice, as well as of more Candour and Temper, than rudely to fly in the Face of, or by any voluntary Act to diſparage thoſe, whom all obſerving Men muſt needs acknowledge to have merited highly at the Nations hands. I thank God I never think of ſome of theſe great Mens ſtout Defence of the Nations Religion and Laws, by Petitioning King <hi>James</hi> againſt reading the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, by an undaunted Appearance at the Council Table, and going in that unconcerned manner to the <hi>Tower,</hi> with the Spirits of Noble and Brave Patriots and Heroes, by ſtanding a Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall:</hi> Further, I never reflect upon that Noble, and almoſt unparallel'd Act of the late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sandcroft,</hi> with others of his Brethren, Addreſſing to King <hi>James,</hi> and telling him to his Face, though with all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and becomingneſs, yet with more than a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46190:14"/>
               <hi>Roman</hi> Courage, all thoſe Faults of his, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had violated the Laws, and incenſed his Subjects againſt him, with an humble deſire to rectifie thoſe Errors of his Government for the time to come: I ſay, I never think of theſe things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoughts of great honour and admiration; and I heartily wiſh for the Churches ſake and their own, they could have complyed with what was required at theirs and all other Mens hands who were in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Places; but ſince they cannot, God forbid but they ſhould have a ſhare in our Charity as well as others, and that they ſhould be no more ſeverely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon than others, whoſe Conſciences and Principles are ſo widely different from the eſtabliſhed Church. And thoſe Men (we know what ſtamp they are of, and what they deſign) who thô they lay at King <hi>James</hi>'s Feet with Lives and Fortunes, even at that very time when theſe great Men ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their Religion and Laws, and ventured their all; I ſay thoſe Men (God knows there are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them) who now when they hear theſe Mens Names, cry, Hang, Damn, Sink them, (Saint like terms indeed) and Drink Healths of Confuſion to them, I muſt begg their Pardon if I tell them, they are ſo far from underſtanding the Commands of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, that they are ſtrangers to the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſuch as the very Heathens think themſelves obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by, and reproach themſelves, if they do not in ſome ſort live up to.</p>
            <p>One thing more, and I have done, if any Man ſhall think and ſuggeſt to others the Commendation I have given theſe Learned Men, reflects upon thoſe Eminent Perſons who were in Epiſcopal Chairs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46190:15"/>
I muſt crave leave to tell them, I ſcorn the thoughts of it, for there were ſome of thoſe as great and good Men as we can deſire to fill a See for the Churches Honour, and the Comfort and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe, both Clergy and Laity, who are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of her Communion; amongſt whom, I muſt tell the World, I mean our own Honourable and Right Reverend Dioceſan, whoſe Name and Vertues will find a room in future Annals and Records, when the Memory of his implacable Enemies on both ſides will periſh.</p>
            <p>And now therefore for a Concluſion, let us Bleſs God for ſuch a King and Queen, who make it their Buſineſs to Conſult and Study the Nations good, by promoting worthy Men themſelves, and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all thoſe Worthy Perſons, whom they found fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the upper Preferments of the Church, before they came to the Throne. May they Proſper in all their juſt and righteous Undertakings: May they live long to Reign over, and to preſerve us againſt all the Deſigns of Prieſts and Jeſuites, and all other wicked Men, who either Envy, or are ready to Plot the ruine of the Nations Happineſs and preſent Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement; and may God cover our great Kings Head in the Day of Battel, give him Victory over all his Enemies, and bring him home again with Triumph to an Obedient and Rejoycing People; to which I do not doubt but all good Men, who love their Religion and their Laws, will ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46190:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
